welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where we go here and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
all right welcome to the stoah and this
was supposed to be posted for a couple
of days ago but just admin stuff I
couldn't just slip through the cracks I
kind of like it this way because you
know this is probably going to be a
messy experiment and um so the idea here
is Jason Jared and myself when we last
talked about mimetic mediation we had
this notion of having this campfire
all right this digital campfire and
people gather around and kind of talk
shop mediation shop about what people
would be good to have around the
campfire together what kind of like
mimetic opponents to have and just have
a heart-to-heart conversation about what
they believe to be true and so what we
thought were kind of our ruff workshop
for today was that Jason Jared and
myself maybe just talked for like 5-10
minutes about what we're doing here and
then we'll open it up to group
discussion so that being said I will
unmute Jason and Jared and we could
begin thanks thank you thank you Peter
well maybe just a brief intro the term
yeah of America mediation was coined
actually by Peter and his article with
Connor Barnes and since then you know a
bunch a bunch of folks have have been
kind of you know thinking about that
term trying to trying to think how it
can be applied you know writing about it
there's like a letter wiki I'm between
me and Peter but there's also more of an
open source document and the idea is
basically it's nothing really new but
it's just you know it seems to be that
especially online there's a lot of
warring subgroups with people that might
have more in common than they think and
especially in these days when we need in
my view a more decentralized distributed
networked alternative to the
establishment which in certain
institutions that seemed not to be
working you know we need to be able to
talk to each other and make sense with
each other even if we don't like each
other so I thought I'd just give that
little intro and that's kind of what
brought us brought us here is something
that you know we've been writing about
anything about for a while but just an
open source concept yeah and and I think
in our last conversation for those who
didn't here we're kind of were exploring
a bit of the boundaries between kind of
deliberate and structured mediation
versus implicit kind of emergent
mediation and I think both of these
things these these approaches you know
it's kind of bottom-up top-down approach
to this need to be considered for sure
and and yeah this is I mean maybe this
is a way of building some structure a
bit of a place for us to start
collaborating and and see what emerges
so so yeah thanks Peter for for creating
the structure and the forum for this -
for this emergent exploration - to come
up my pleasure
so the question I have for you two guys
looking maybe we can jam for a couple of
minutes it's coming to mind is this a
street I did recently about like if it's
right now I don't really give a
about the medium of broadcast of content
broadcast like oh my podcast with the
YouTube channel I have I just threw up
and I thought it like huh there's like a
conflation sometimes between the spirit
of a community that arises in these
domains versus the actual like broadcast
output of it the medium for that and I'm
like huh so if you kind of focus more on
the ladder the medium for content
broadcasting that's going to create a
medic tribes
but if you focus on this digital
campfire and build real communities
around it there's a potential to create
embody tribes so that's coming to my
right now just maybe wanted to see if
anything landed there for you guys yeah
so maybe maybe flesh out a little bit
what we talked about with it with this
idea from what I remember is that you
know I know a few people have been kind
of thinking along these lines of having
say a YouTube channel that that is not
there's kind of a you know it might be
managed by somebody but you know you
might you can have any kind of set of
people you know could be a pair three
people who can record something and put
it on you know put it on this channel
that you know is basically with the
theme of you know trying to have a
sincere and constructive conversation
and so you know it might be people who
would you know have been beefing on
Twitter or you know and some other
platform and you know they weren't
really having a constructive dialogue
with each other it was getting
contentious and this would be
opportunity to be like kind of like with
letter wiki it's like hey why don't you
folks write a letter to each other well
it's kind of like the you know the
analogy analog of that but on on
something like YouTube or some other
video platform where you could be like
hey let's get on and have a recorded
video and I guess doesn't have to be
recorded but and so this channel would
just be you know you would see this you
go to the channel and you'd be like you
know whoever's part of this network and
and who wants to you know so maybe you
would sign up like letter wiki whoever
wants to sign up and be you know start a
conversation they can do that and put it
up to the channel is that is that kind
of what you had in mind Peter for this
digital campfire thing yeah yeah
something like that it's I guess to the
even more central was just a space for
people to kind of spit ball and workshop
about what would be how to have an
emetic mediate in this Lana liminal war
that were in her culture war that were
in and because when I talked to you
yesterday you mentioned you know that
certain spat or beef that is happening
and I wasn't aware of it or you talked
about any also talked about Richard and
Jack
yeah and I don't know that they had a
spat I might go I said hurt and that was
just like you know you nailed that match
right there and I don't know what's
gonna happen but that's a perfect match
and I am I was ignorant of that panis
fat but if we have more people gather
around the digital campfire that
resonate with mimetic mediation then we
can kind of source out those those
potential matches and then brainstorm
ways to figure out how to make it happen
mm-hmm
so I think that is the the essence yeah
and one thing I would like to emphasize
and maybe maybe you might disagree but
it doesn't even have to be on the topic
of what they were spouting about it
could just be a conversation getting to
know each other and and they can you
know do that without recording or they
could record it it could also be kind of
like we're doing here with a group where
you know they're having a conversation
for 20 minutes or so and then they open
it up and other people can kind of help
diagnose what you know if there is
disagreement where is the source
disagreement you know to kind of of
course you know you'd you'd want it to
be people who you know that that weren't
you know rushing to one side and you
know something like that it would be you
know people who could play the role of
memetic mediators I guess yeah you know
or Eggman you know performative agnostic
or something like that
yeah something that's that's coming up
for me and I know I mentioned it before
I'm definitely not allergic to conflict
and I know that the conflict is kind of
inherent in the selection of the of the
people here if we're kind of trying to
bridge ideological or tribal gaps but I
do think you know to kind of keep with
this metaphor of the campfire the the
reason that it one of the components
that seems to be very rich there is that
there's kind of a warmth right and it's
like providing a you know a a source of
life for everybody involved so there's
kind of like a an inherent positive
frame that needs to be included as in as
well and and that being said
you know this doesn't have weight I
don't want to like systematize it so
much but I think if we can think about
how we're framing these conversations
depending on who's going to be in the
conversations it'll be very important
and sometimes that I think that'll mean
that we have to find some topic that
there's some agreement already on and
maybe seeing you know slightly to tell
you differences you know and then some
some tribes are very comfortable with
conflict and they want to brawl it out
and they're fine and afterwards they can
hug and and and you know and and and not
not break any bridges or anything like
that but there has to be some sort of
conviviality or pro-social orientation I
think if we gonna if we're gonna be set
in these these dialogues up so so it
feels really live right now is something
that both of you said I really like what
you said Jason that you know doesn't
have to be about disagreements it could
just be about like relating in front of
the campfire yeah and it looks like at
the edge of my thinking with all the
mimetic tribal culture where stuff like
all the propositions are just like red
herrings for just sort of like you know
like trigger beefs that they're having
or emotional like you know they get
triggered in a certain way and so and
then going with to you what you just
said Jared it's like finding the right
angle or the right topic the right frame
that like speech to both of their day
moans and then setting up a situation so
they gather around the digital campfire
so they can have what you just described
Jason mmm yeah well the question is how
much do we set up the frame and how much
do they set up the frame right because
if they're if it's something like letter
wiki where you know one person they're
both signed up to the to let our wiki
and they invite the other one to start a
letter like they're the ones that are
really setting the frame and so I'm
wondering how you know like how do you
balance the individual is involved kind
of setting the frame versus you know
ensuring that you have some kind of you
know conviviality and constructiveness
to the conversation
[Music]
yeah it feels if you know my my
intuition is that you know since there's
going to be such a diversity in in the
dynamics of who's going to be attending
it feels like there there needs to be
some it would be very beneficial to have
some sort of process to go through and
as I'm thinking it through it might be
you know answer these three questions as
you're coming into it like you know what
are your goals for this conversation you
know what are you afraid of of being
triggered by or something like that kind
of error in your own ideological biases
and making it transparent so that
everybody's kind of aware of what the
agenda is and something like oh I I
think we'd have to like actually sit
down and kind of think through and we
can probably use some of the previous
discussions and the letter wiki's and
stuff like that to kind of boil down
like these essential pork point points
of memetic mediation and make sure each
of them is kind of being is visible for
everybody that's involved involved or
something like that but I'd like it for
it to be to your point Jason something
that they emerge that they arrive at and
it's kind of meaning every time it's
gonna be a completely different frame
that they're setting but people within
the conversation Alonso that are doing
it so let's open up to the group in a
moment about let's maybe do one I'll
have a final thought and maybe we can do
one around the final thoughts and then
we'll open it up and ki just asked can
someone define mimetic mediation for me
please we're gonna let's pause that for
a moment because this is sort of a let's
pause that for a moment because I kind
of want to kick out about this right now
and not get to the 101 territory so the
final thought here is for me before we
open up to the group is as the kind of a
marketing angle and you know I've done
hundreds of events in person and then
it's like you kind of like want to
market a certain way and I've done like
35 events here the store already and how
the event is marketed or how its framed
how it's like the coin it attracts a
certain people has like a bias to
attract the filter is kind of for the
right
people in a way it's marketed correctly
and leaning into kind of my
sensitivities on the culture war and
being able to sort of method act all
these different reality tunnels if you
can do that well enough then you can
kind of find the angle potentially of
what speaks to them and they find the
angle at what speaks the other person
and then maybe find the intersection
between the two and then that's what you
present to them like hey would you like
to come to the store for this so my side
could be wrong here I do like the idea
that we have to let it emerge but
especially people are don't want to even
talk to each other it's like almost like
some of the the front end work it was on
up to us to figure out how to seduce
them in a way mm-hmm yeah so it seems
like you could have both you could you
could have you know something that's
that's kind of you know like one of
somebody notices a couple people not
having constructive dialogue but you
know perhaps they could and they you
know then they they workshop with a
field of people marketing you know kind
of a framing of the conversation and
they present it to the folks and then
they do it we're not and then people who
spontaneously say like hey I've had some
like not-so-great interactions with use
day on Twitter let's have a conversation
let's record it and let's let's just try
and go into this with good faith and
perhaps we can ask somebody else a third
party to sit in there and be the
quote-unquote mediator you know not that
the mediator will say much but you know
we'll be somebody that both parties can
trust to you know not not to tip the
scales in one direction or another yeah
it sounds like we've thrown a lot out
I'm kind of curious yeah
so uh yeah just I'm gonna set the frame
here that this is a admittedly a
high-level discussion and if you have no
idea what the mimetic mediation is
we did a Jason did a nice little brief
intro so if you came late and of course
that you missed that you can go to that
cultural white paper and just search
magnetic mediation to get maybe you just
read that section of it but this is
pretty high level and we're and we're
gonna keep it high level or at least I
have a desire to keep it high level
because that being said anything and I
trust everyone's a sermon and the
so just kind of unmute yourself let's
see if everyone has that option we all
have that option so just unmute yourself
and just kind of share what what came
alive for your what you you want to add
to the conversation yeah sorry I'll just
quickly interrupt I never talk to Jared
directly hello Jared
one thing I just like came up to me when
when Jason was talking is um you know
you described you know two people that
had a disagreement on Twitter they then
get into this space and then they have a
third mediator right but then we also
talked about okay what if we have other
people in the space listening in and
then after a 20 minute or 30 minute who
knows how long back and forth these
people can then like now on mute or
unmute themselves and then put in their
you know inputs could state they I mean
that then you just have so much a wealth
of information to draw from in so many
different angles to perhaps yeah mediate
between the two and that that could be
super beneficial instead of just a third
like just three people so what do you
think of that mm-hm I think it might
vary depending on on the you know the
individual interaction so I mean one
thing I'd be concerned about with the
big group is that you know it becomes a
pile-on on one side right and so it
would have to be in the group people who
could who could somewhat play the role
of performative agnostic meaning that
they can kind of put aside their views a
little bit and just try to help clarify
the conversation like like where people
misunderstanding each other you know
like like maybe when you said this you
react this way they you know like maybe
you were misinterpreting them and you
know and they could you maybe
interpreted this way then the other
person says is that fair to you and yes
it kind of just how kind of mediate and
the nice thing about just one or two
mediators is that you can beforehand you
know you can get the buy-in of both
participants saying hey these two people
you know do they you know do you you
trust these two people enough to mediate
this conversation but I think it will
depends
you know personally honest in this
situation and I think sometimes having
you know eight people like like now
extra people make sense and sometimes
maybe maybe less or sometimes none you
know if if the two people think that
they can handle themselves you know and
they don't need a third mediator they
can also ought for that as well what's
what's coming to mind there is two it's
like let's say if there's two matches or
two people that we think would be good
to talk to each other but then there's
sort of resistance that they have to
talk to one another
it's like it's almost like when I'm
viewing the stoah space is like being an
artist of experience so each session is
kind of different and it could be like
you know United Jason did empathy
circles for example right maybe although
we do an empathy circle for one session
maybe something's as simple as just
sharing your emotional reality in front
of someone you don't really like or you
don't like their ideas and what keep the
mine was when Jack Murphy came on a a
couple of days ago you know some
sessions I opened up with like a sharing
my emotional reality some we don't but I
felt like you know what he has a lot of
his liminal kind of alpha males in the
audience and you know he's like a alpha
male so I'm like you know I'm gonna
share my emotional reality I'm gonna say
that I'm nervous right now which I was
and then that I think invited him to say
that he was nervous because he shared it
when he he went up is he thought like
okay I'm not a philosopher or like what
am I doing here
and I felt him more and I think the
people felt the more so imagine if it's
like Richard and Jack just kind of share
their emotions just some like that
right and so they build that that bond
beyond the propositions yeah that's what
I was gonna bring up is the whole point
of a medic mediation the way I see it is
not so much to resolve things at the
mimetic level but to resolve things at a
deeper embodied level like a felt like
that the the felt bond with another
person that when you
to that place the propositions sort of
lose their there they're holding their
strength on you and it's it's not really
about that anymore it's like well these
are just tools that we're using to try
and figure things out together so the
the vulnerability fostering
vulnerability that aspect of mediation I
think is really important and I think
about this a lot in terms of family and
close friends in my local community like
physical local community and people I
already have some sort of a bond with
and you know I've just been mindful of
of up settling into that bond when I go
to have a discussion you know about
which you know there are propositions
where we when we disagree about things
it's like well let's get on the same
page at a deeper level and and then see
where we're at and that that seems to
make a huge difference at least at least
for me when I when I'm looking at
someone else's worldview through that
felt sense of shared relationality yeah
belonging with this person yeah yeah
there's there's a the feeling into the
evoked emotional responses and
displaying it verbally is like you know
it's a very quick way to do move out of
the ideology and back into the body and
then seeing that it's happening across
the board it's creating some sort of
connection or agreement that hey we're
both bodies you know kind of we're both
humans and so yeah the embodied
component is really big
yeah it's interesting you know on one
end of the spectrum I think we had a
Peter be in a conversation a while ago
with some of the letter wiki folks and
we were talking about what a medic
mediator would look like in that text
form - and there's like a couple quick
things that kind of came up you know one
of them being like the loominator
requesting a definition because they
noticed that there were playing a
semantics game or you know in this case
we're saying hey let's do a state check
and talk about our emotional place right
now other times it could be you know the
mediator especially in these
conversations I think a lot of their
values to kind of say hey I'm seeing
that I agree with both of you but in
different ways so it's like the fact
that they could see that they that it's
possible to to agree on both sides even
though they see you their selves as
diametrically opposed it's almost like
there's you know there's a very large
tool that can be wielded by the mimetic
mediators and and if we were to make
this if the mediators were if there's a
lot of them as opposed to just a few key
people it might be it might be good to
kind of put together a toolkit as well
you know like here are some of the go-to
things like you know if things are going
off the rails here's a here's a few
things in the playbook to kind of create
some you know break the tension or the
conflict or something like that to you
yeah just a random thought I've got to
come up Peter do you see so on one end
of the spectrum we're talking about kind
of an open space where it's many people
can gather but like how how how often do
you think there would be like a very
common you know maybe it's us three that
would be kind of setting the frame for
this and maybe even interacting and the
conversations or do we where we get the
open source route seems to be a bigger
thing but you know it's it's also then
something like a toolkit or creating
some more method and things like that
would be in hand at least needed what I
was thinking was just sort of like that
I guess tease out the vision or the
impulse of this kind of event is I like
the idea
the three of us Griffen for five to 15
minutes and then open up to the group to
talk about what exactly madam AK
mediation is for the Provost session or
what it could be in this liminal war and
then who would need to have you know to
be mediated in the culture war and then
I kind of imagine like different maybe
whoever's inspired to go about it could
just do like a project if you know like
okay yeah like I can I can I could
probably do it like a mash those two
together and then you know whatever
emerges from this and I think if we
record these and in broadcast some of
them if people don't veto it then I
imagine that kind of inspiration could
just spread so I I was definitely
thinking the more open-source realm and
I also add I like the idea of a toolkit
and it also could be just sort of like
certain moves conversational moves
someone could do to be a good mediator
and what's coming alive right now I was
just talking to Daniel if his engine
does the metagame master my here at the
store and you know that kind of a
postmodern and skill set where you hear
a word right like a verbal dispute if
you hear a word that triggers someone
and just kind of pause and then just
allow the person to describe the felt
sense reality of that word like how do
they feel when they say it you know
because like if you took think about any
words like the Kyle was talking about
how tomorrow died for me recently if you
think that the concept of tomorrow
tomorrow has a certain felt since
reality behind it and like forget about
the propositional accuracy of what that
what that really means but it's kind of
like flesh out what what do you feel
like when racism comes up right or some
other kind of hot term and just talk
about and let's see if we can build a
relationship with those emotional
realities
I think one thing that is the first well
the first or second thing to decide is
that who's what is the star of the show
so is this role model is the mediator
going to be visible and is that the star
or is it is the mediator going to be
invisible and is that the star or is the
ultimate combination of a chord an
agreement is that the star and I'm
thinking I like the idea of warmth and
so there have there has to be something
there has to be either a visible or
invisible
you know structure somewhere right
that's to make you don't want the all
the videos to be just you know random
videos you want them to be maybe proving
a point or you know if it's emergent
there's no who's going to want to watch
1 through 10 videos that are all
completely different that's my thought
curious
of others others in this group who
haven't talked yet have any ideas I'll
speak to that but I'm sorry I'll speak
to it about it from a work approach so
in terms of a conflict example you could
throw me and Jordan on the table I
haven't been gentleman by any means at
the same time if your goal is the end
product of developing a work then that
needs to be what people are focused on
by and large I don't care what
your opinion is as long as it's informed
if it's informed it could be different
than mine so there's no requirement for
any kind of concordance but if people
are going to bring to the table
and distractions that's a whole
different deal so one of the most
effective worth relationships I ever had
was with this dude named Simon we always
saw things 92 180 degrees different but
we continuously push things back and
forth back and forth by the time we were
done we had a very optimal solution to
whatever problem it was we were
addressing at the time people need to
set the ego stuff aside and start
looking at what the big picture goal is
and it's not attached to you it's not
attached to your outcome like we're
trying to do something bigger here I
think some of the some of the community
building needs to be around engaging in
mutual projects together where there is
some kind of difficulty because I mean
you need some commonality of shared
experience in order to build a sense of
community and if that experience is
arduous then the depth of camaraderie is
definitely higher yeah I think that's a
great point I mean of course the
challenge is you know this is mainly
from online space you know it's it's
hard to just get kind of you know I
agree that having a larger goal in terms
of you know why do we want to mediate
with each other besides just everyone
you know feeling nice about it well
because you know there's a lot going on
in the world right now and you know we
need real collaboration
to you know improve our response you
know resilience and our collective
intelligence and be able to actually you
know make us you know make the world a
better place I think a big chunk of that
is just bringing people more into adult
mode instead of the coddling and there's
everybody okay well we're adults we've
got to get done here if you've got
something that needs con that has some
kind of attention take it offline but in
the meantime there needs to be some kind
of a focus even if it's just project
based but I think a big part of it is
encouraging people to develop the kind
of skills that keep them in adult state
so less on the body and the emotions but
more I mean if there's always a balance
between the getting caught up your
theater head up your ass with hyper
rationalism and not having any kind of
grounded reality to you know emotional
realism but at the same time the
emotional stuff is almost always just a
trap it's an easy way for people to
throw their little hook in divert the
course of the conversation towards
whatever and they're seeking for their
own gratification as opposed to staying
on focus to what the actual task is and
doing the planning doing the exercises
that need to get done to see that to
fruition and I probably sound kind of
tactical because my background is soccer
and systems architecture and heavily it
towards the engineering side of things
not a motive but in terms of having to
get done in big complex situations
that's how it works
those are the tools that's need to
engage in order to reach those goals
yeah it's it's
interesting I think we're so at least in
my mind there's kind of an implied
project in just the phrasing mimetic
mediation and that is simply that
decentralized and a collective approach
to building a new new ways of operating
and collaborating is not happening right
now and so the mimetic mediation as
opposed to being or it's predominantly
focused on kind of the in-between space
the in between projects right so it's
like the more mediation that's happening
the easier it is for ideas and memes to
prop cross propagate across different
groups and then you know next time you
know next time the software product is
created it might take in to
consideration different different lenses
and ideas because they were talking to
people that they weren't they weren't
talking to previously and then other
thing I'd like to kind of throw out
there as well is that I think conflict
is you know the the predominant frame
that we're talking about here but I
think that we can also talk about just
simply disconnection I think a lot of
these campfires should be getting people
together that have no idea that they
exist and maybe they don't even disagree
but they need to be talking to each
other right so it's like this is it's
this prop this cross propagation you
know that the encouraging the
permeability of the the membranes of
each of our groups is kind of the
primary big-picture focus but you know
Robert and and Jason both you guys are
mentioning that it seems like there
needs to be some more micro takeaways as
well even if it's in one conversation or
a smaller midterm project or something
like that too
I like the idea nothing as you know it's
hard to think of what what kind of
projects might be readily available to
graft on to that yeah so I think I have
something coming up and yeah what Jason
said didn't resonate with me and and
uh-oh kind of flesh out why and then
kind of present my like working theory
on this I do agree like I like the adult
metaphor that an adult adults can get in
the room together and figure out the
super ordinate goal that unites them
there and then they kind of like to
reason figure out what the to do
right but when you're in a situation and
like culture war 2.0 and they're all
these medic tribes I understand reality
differently how do you get them to have
a super ordinate goal by just allowing
them to talk to each other
they don't talk to each other and so I
think the beats are the movements and I
could be mistaken about this but it's
step one build the capacity for good
faith right built the capacity to have
good faith for someone and I would argue
that's emotional capacity you know
actually kind of like have a heart are
connected with similar or kind of feel
them then step two then reason together
hey Jess like I get to get to the brass
tacks of the proposition what's what is
true and what not I will hold on and my
sense is that that that is sort of one
of the essence of the digital campfires
to get that kind of heart-to-heart like
what Jason said earlier and and kind of
like the the trickster in me is like
each session and this is the answer
Roberts question each sort of memetic
project that could emerge from these
spitballing sessions could have its own
super ordinate goal that speaks to the
two people who should be speaking with
each other so maybe it's an empathy to
circles maybe it's an anti debate maybe
just a good old debate maybe it's just
like a sharing a circle so that's what
came up
second responder over my life experience
I think it's less important to try to
reach everybody as it as opposed to
reach the people who are actually
thinking and they're not many of them
they're hard to find but if we can get
them working together then we've got
something to work with
trying to bootstrap everybody up is a
long and tedious and more time of
fruitless process you need to build
trust relationships on two vectors I
need to trust your capacity and your
intentions and the only way I'm going to
see that is through collaborations of
experience working together I think
speaking of trust I agree with that line
of thinking and I should say that I also
appreciate um the the intention of
transparency and open source projects
creating a toolkit and having a
beneficial process to go through for
like questions that can be answered for
people to have these mimetic mediations
um I'd like to point out that I I enjoy
the stola for the the the definitely
experimental process that it can be and
I am completely an intro and I keep
saying that every time I do come onto
the space because I am I really am
learning from scratch uh these these
kinds of philosophical topics so I say
that and I started with trust because um
I had to find this particular session I
I went to the stellar calm which I go on
there like every time to check out the
events and I'm speaking in this kind of
tone because yeah this is the kind of
like personality then I go into the
stove Oh with sometimes um so I clicked
on stove accom and I saw that this event
um was going to be at 1:00 p.m. but I
was on at 1:30 I was like oh wow it's
probably already done um but I was like
hey there's still a link here so I
clicked on it clicked on it and it said
3:30 on the Google Docs and like damn
guys I can still join so I joined um and
I'm really glad that I did because I'm
learning a lot and I and I want to
participate in it and I love being able
to participate in these things I'm
learning from different types of people
I love like project-based focuses on
focus eyes focus I like a project-based
focus because it does lead towards
problem-solving methods that are framed
in ways that lead to informed
discussions and that balance of
emotional the emotions and the the logic
and the reason is is really really
needed in all of us that embodied way of
thinking and that um that that highly
philosophical like logical proposition
statements ideas are all are both
important in their own ways so to be
able to put those things together and
have the space to do so thank you Peter
and thank you to the people who are
coming in here so if you just need to
say those things I have a question so
like Jason said right like people who
can get things done they are the ones
that matter and how Peter and the others
are kind of trying to frame you're
asking like you know what about the
others who want to come in and learn who
want kind of help and kind of putting
things together want to be a part so if
we had mediate between these two
different viewpoints the only thing that
again keeps coming up for me is the fact
that you need a common shared project on
which we can then distribute the
processing right so if you distribute
processing right everybody becomes a
node everybody is allowed to go into
their rabbit hole bring back what they
can bring then we sit together and in a
given particular context we examine that
together right and those that need to
take leaps take leave those that need to
mediate mediate so each one kind of
moves on to the spectrum of their
personality and they kind of like work
on that project together from there we
can actually see what words what is not
work you know how other what are the
frameworks we supposed to employ these
kind of things because what we do it
like what I do at my work right be
building a platform where we are trying
to see how we can allow people to kind
of move out and distribute their
cognitive capacity so rather than me
trying to do something on my own how can
I get for example let me just use an
example this is easy right let's say I
need to study about a subject cognitive
psychology right
I can read one book at a time now if I
call Jared I called the Jason I called
Peter and I said hey man this is what I
want to learn about you is also
interested oh you guys looking to stick
to so come along so we gave you
something
Egypt has read five different books on
the subject meat country so we have
distributed that then we come back just
like how Jason said we trust each other
for our capacity all of that stuff and
then we go and we kind of like distill
what we've learned them we compiled all
these five from the five different
vantage points five different notes we
compile all of that information and from
there we start kind of like pulling in
and pulling out so when that pulley what
needs to stay and what needs to go
conversation starts that's when the
actual mimetic mediation kind of flag
comes in because I I personally believe
that coming from yes culture war yes but
that's move now right
so rather than trying to bring people
from extremes together we should come to
the middle and see who are the people on
either side who are closer to the middle
and what are the strategies that we can
do to engage them and once we kind of
build from that core place where we can
see okay you know these people will
invest time and energy into this how
from there then can be like start
scaling outwards and pull their you know
people at the extremities to that kind
of country so that would be the strategy
I would employ yeah if I can speak to
the campfire for a minute
when this covert stuff is done I've got
a nice spot up here just outside of
Toronto we can maybe do it as a city I
think a lot of the stuff that we're
dealing with in terms of subject matter
and information within it it's all
exceedingly complex but I think in large
part there's a couple of things that are
missing off the table in this
conversation I think there are a lot of
late learning methodologies within
information technology that are easily
adaptable to the cognitive stuff and I
think one of the things that's kind of
missing in the big picture of the
discussion is some kind of grounding in
you know formalized mystery tradition
I went around the discussion I just I
don't see a whole lot of depth of people
who have actually engaged that pathway
and I don't see a lot of people talking
about it
I mean from personal perspective I've
been involved in Freemasonry since 2002
and as an institutional model both
they're sort of the ritual model in
terms of engaging or inculcating lessons
to the individual I think is very
effective yeah the use of the object
lesson and I think the institutional
model where you take someone you
basically start them at the SI gate and
you bring them in and put them through
all these seats or chairs that are
required to run an organization
effectively and as you're bringing them
through you're basically progressing
them as a person and also training them
to be capable of actually running the
organization so I think there's some
value in that model that I haven't
really seen brought to the table in any
kind of depth yet yeah so I just had a
couple thoughts I know these kind of
in-between space conversations and kind
of speculation and Barry Peters point we
just kind of started with this high
level frame and not quite in the needy
greedy yet and then you know Jason when
you showed us your campfire I kind of
felt why I was feeling kind of weird
about this like what are we making what
are we doing what project what are the
deliverables from this and I think that
that was quickly or he came to me very
quickly when I saw that campfire and
that's the sense like when that last
time I was at a campfire there's there's
no agenda it was it was just let's enjoy
each other's presence and have
conversations and relate and build
connections after we've were done
working for the day you know we've been
we've been goal-oriented and and and and
collaborating on a daily basis and and
is a time for us kind of reflect get
some distance and bring in some other
perspectives so maybe that that might be
why I was having some kind of resistance
to the the extreme the extremely kind of
hyper focused goal-oriented face and and
you know this also speaks to other work
environments I know apples kind of
renowned for for building their offices
to to in a way that promotes collisions
from very different perspectives you
know they put the the bathrooms all on
one side so that all these people have
to be that our different compartments
are kind of running into each other and
having these chance conversations with
no agenda but those those types of
environments are usually really most
kind of rich insight and unique
processes emerge and that's because it's
in this unordered space and I largely
well I think they have to be intimately
connected mimetic mediation feels like
it's a lot more about the space in
between the projects and the goals and
and and yeah so yeah and that's just uh
yeah I guess but but you know I'm a
goal-oriented guy and then I want to be
heads down doing stuff with projects
every day but sometimes I just want to
shoot the of the campfire in place
with the Stars fun that no Dino photo
wave yeah on that note Jason as Jared
say I like that because the hyper goal
thing doesn't resonate with me when I
think of this project of memetic
mediation and if I were to kind of put
myself in that mindset almost like a
sense of arrogance emerges oh I know
what the superordinate goal is and just
like that campfire thing that you
mentioned Jared and then I keep
returning what you said earlier Jason
just sort of like just crack open a beer
with someone at the campfire and I think
I got it again is he said he was talking
about how Vice broke up and his
heuristic was that like yeah you know
when you stop grabbing beer with your
co-founder you know shit's gonna hit the
fan and so like the thought emerges like
who do we want to have a kind of
encourage to have a beer with each other
around this kind of memetic campfire
yeah I have to say I I'm kind of leaning
both in what Peter and Jared are saying
is that I think the superordinate goal
come comes later I think the you know
for me the the main issue and I don't
think it's that some people are thinking
and some people are run by their
emotions I disagree with that diagnosis
I think that a lot of people have the
capacity to think but because of their
ideologies which is you know tied to
their identity and emotions is causing
them not to talk to each other when they
could actually have you know very
constructive more logical propositional
conversations but because they have some
kind of allergy to an ideological
allergy that they never even get in the
room with each other and so I I I just I
just don't see that with the world in
the way that you do Jason fair enough
maybe people do I see where you're
coming from but I I think this idea of
putting aside your emotions I think you
can't do that because the emotions are
still in the background and they're
gonna come back and bite ya like you
need like the idea that before you can
engage in a goal or in a logical
propositional conversation you just need
to get comfortable with each other a
basic bonding process as we talked about
before or not and I relate this to to
like Kagan stages as an analogy where
you know Stage three is the more sub
ideological relational stage and I think
you need a good foundation there before
you start getting into the more like
let's develop coherent ideology together
or let's develop you know something else
you know a set of values together and
that might involve being vulnerable and
you know allowing yourself to be
emotional in front of each other and but
in the safe environment where it's not
going to blow up and you know cause even
further division well add a little bit
there too there really is there's no
conversations that don't have emotions
involved right like you know if we just
look at psychological research we find
that rationalization is the predominant
is rationalizing our emotional reactions
in many ways and so this is the medic
mediation what we're doing especially
when we were talking about getting in
touch with the felt sense this is
showing us our own boundaries and in
trying to you know say okay well this is
normally something I can't talk about
and talk about because it's just too
ridiculous to me or to or it's absurd or
it's it's it's violent or it's whatever
it is but you know it the more we kind
of feel into those spaces and and relate
with each other kind of there's a
dissolving that happens and it actually
allows our thinking to be more broad and
inclusive as opposed to stuck into very
our kind of conditioned reality of this
is what's right this is what's wrong and
stuff like that so so yeah just to kind
of add some more meat on the bones of
Jason's emotional comments when you have
those hooks into the limbic system the
default mode network or anything that
kicks off the limbic system is going to
kick off the default mode Network and
kind of drop down the the working
feeling of what you're actually capable
of so the emotional states I kind of
look at them as like indicator lights on
a car if they're telling you something
you've missed something in a situational
awareness up to that point they're kind
of like the last resort indicators so I
yeah the process is we're trying to
figure out how not to let those
indicator lights interfere with us
actually operating the machine so yeah
take that whole hell of a lot of work
constipation is no healthier than
diarrhea and transience of the process
of the system so we can't be just you
know eating our and swallowing it
down and not coming to terms with any
kind of the realistic consequences about
emotive stress or anything else like
that but at the same time watching
people they play that game pretty hard
like a lot of people dwell and revel in
their misery
do large degree you can see that we're
something that has upset them they just
glom onto it and attached to it and
won't let that thing go or is it they
can just soften the grip a little bit
step back then it's a little easier to
walk through and process that kind of
stuff
let's say one of them so there's two
different goals there's a goal for a
resolution of an an ideological question
I don't think that we care what the
answers are we'll find out the goal is
to show something - I like the words now
warmth and space and I agreed that it's
emergent in some sense it's a chat by
the campfire it doesn't have a direction
but it also does have a goal in another
sense and that goal isn't isn't an
intellectual correctness or nothing's
going to be produced it's it's something
about connecting and it's the space has
to have some sort of role model though
and I don't know how to do that but
something is pedagogic write something
and it all just be structured and not a
third person being a mediator but
something there has to be that point but
that point is different from like what
is the correct answer so we're not I
mean in my view we're not looking for
the correct answer we're looking for
what I what I said so I'm just going to
jump in this time I want to invite
anyone who hasn't spoken if they feel
called to speak
if not then me Jason and Jared will just
kind of do her closing thoughts and
we'll close up today let's give a moment
for anyone who who
to speak who hasn't spoken yet I'm
started looking at you James
I met a modern friend you want me to say
something Peter I'm curious if you have
any thoughts well you know it's
interesting just seeing everybody's
perspectives
you know I am more of a cultural
theorist I guess you might say so even
though I'm by far not an academic I like
to understand the sort of social
historical analysis behind this and then
see if I can't deconstruct it and then
see what it takes to reconstruct it that
makes sense
so you know it's just what are you you
know if you're gonna if you're going to
in other words it's almost like you have
to have but and then you've got to kind
of draw out what is the what is that
thing that needs to be mediated and it's
gonna depend on very complex individual
and situational analysis so you know
there's a whole there's a whole lot of
talk here that is you know just by you
know the eight of us remember in your
talk and that's gonna take a lot longer
than an hour the kind of figure out but
I mean that's just kind of where I'm at
you know I is you know Peter here I kind
of think of it in terms of you know
cultural areas and generations and and
you know I'm right now I've been reading
a lot of literature on the academic
history of the generation gastrin kind
of an anomaly mediate that over the
course of history which is that just
what I
what to do but have nobody probably
cares about that specific instance but
you know that's just what I'm thinking
so oh cool thank you beyond speaking so
how about will close up maybe just one
minute each guys like Jared and Jason
let's just do a one-minute closing
thoughts and then we'll end it today
mm-hmm I think we don't we it's hard to
anticipate what the problems are gonna
be that we're gonna need to be able to
collaborate on in an intelligent way and
make sense with each other and so for me
mimetic mediation is kind of set in the
condition for that to happen when the
need to collaborate will you know will
arise you know I think this Kovas
situation maybe is a good example where
you know if you look at the information
ecology you know different groups knew
about the the virus and the potential
danger of the virus you know very early
and groups that don't normally talk to
each other right and they're kind of
medically sealed off from each other and
if they could have been communicating
much earlier you know that might have
had a greater impact on the overall prep
you know probit preparation of the
culture because you know a lot of a lot
of these folks like on Twitter do have a
lot of influence right and so for me
it's not about you know finding the
problem that you want to solve right
away it's it's getting people
comfortable with each other and at least
respectful of each other's views such
that they're not gonna strawman each
other and you know that such that when
problems do arise they can very quickly
connect and you know work together to
get you know to get something
accomplished so that's that's that's my
thinking
I can go next and then Jared maybe even
close yeah lots of things I thought that
was a lot of a lot of great metaphors
and thoughts came up here and a lot of
seeds were definitely planted so I
appreciated of this sort of mediation
campfire I like that and this is last
minute we asked the juicy conversation
so imagine if they had like a week
advance of the post of this what could
happen and then I just I wanted to flake
something that something I think it was
Jason and Peter said and the way I
interpreted I felt that there was a
conveyance of what I felt I was
misunderstood or something that I think
that was projected a certain kind of
narrative or framework on me that I
didn't agree with and I had that could
be totally my miss reading of it but I
noticed when I had that I got triggered
I got emotion I got emotionally
triggered alright I just wanted to like
like let's fight let's suppose
debate right I just wanted to
get in that mode and so let's assume
that is this all my my end or let's
just you know another reality let's
assume that I was misinterpreted right I
think for me personally at my edge and I
think this is a good skills that they
have is be very very comfortable with
being misinterpreted yeah it's funny
that you say that being misinterpreted
because I just uh I talked to my wife a
lot about how I'm very frustrated with
language because I don't think there's
any way that I can express what I'm
actually feeling and when I hear I say
myself say it on my own that doesn't
sound like at all
I don't know that does not it and so it
is it's definitely a struggle yeah my
main thought here right now is actually
I hate to say it but I'm kind of
thinking that the mimetic mediation
might have some colloquial assumptions
baked into it especially the mediation
port port point in the sense that it
seems to be focused on the resolution of
conflict and you know you know the the
simple rebranding that comes to mind
right now is like what would I think if
we called it a memetic campfire like
that just changes the frame completely
right because we kind of speaking to the
fact that this campfire metaphor has so
many so much less resolution oriented
goals it's just just let's be together
and let's let's have some interpersonal
contact
so yeah I don't know just some thoughts
but you have that being said mimetic
mediation itself I still think is kind
of like the underlying long-term goal or
orientation at the same time but but
it's a long new magnesian is a long game
we're not changing minds in single
conversations too slow
slow process of relating so yeah I don't
know just just just a few of my thoughts
there that I like that okay so if anyone
wants to veto this recording just
message me in the chat box now or find
me elsewhere a public post maybe later
today or tomorrow and if you veto it I
will delete it if not it'll probably go
up on YouTube other than that I'm just
going to debrief with Jason and Jared
hopefully and then we'll see what we can
do next so thanks everyone for coming on
yeah thanks everyone